<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.9.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2021-03-04T00:20:54+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Luca Grandinetti’s Portfolio</title><subtitle>Data Scientist Consultant | Design and development of machine learning models</subtitle><author><name>Luca Grandinetti</name></author><entry><title type="html">Dinosaur Classifier</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/03/03/dinosaur-classifier.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Dinosaur Classifier" /><published>2021-03-03T01:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-03-03T01:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/03/03/dinosaur-classifier</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/03/03/dinosaur-classifier.html">&lt;p&gt;I was born in the year Jurassic Park was released and when I was 4 years old the US 
remake of Godzilla was distibuted. This means that as a child, like many of my 
generation, I was obsessed with large reptiles! Back in the day I was a bit confused 
about the different types of dinosaurs (T-rex, brontosaurus, stregosaurus, triceratops),
which is why today I have developed an image dinosaur classifier that can also recognize
the king of monsters from prehistoric reptiles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;in-the-beginning-was-the-data&quot;&gt;In the beginning was the Data&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first thing you need to do in order to train a classifier is to collect data.
 Unfortunately, the public datasets focus much more on irises than dinosaurs, 
 which is why I decided to build the training set with data extracted 
 via a web scraper.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To use it, you can use my notebook available &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/glep93/google_image_scraper/blob/main/Scrap%20images.ipynb&quot;&gt;here.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The web scraper search on google the dinosaur and save all images related to it. All this 
images will be labelled as the search string. This means that an image found searching 
the world ‘T-rex’ is classified as ‘T-rex’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-classifier&quot;&gt;The classifier&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Developing a classifier from scratch is definitely something very elegant, but transfer 
learning nowadays is the best and fastest way to create an image classifier.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The architecture of this model is very simple, the first non-drawable layer extracts the
 main features of the image and is taken from 
 &lt;a href=&quot;https://tfhub.dev/google/tf2-preview/mobilenet_v2/feature_vector/4&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;,
 while a second dense layer is trained to identify the different classes 
 (T-rex, brontosaurus, stregosaurus, triceratops and Godzilla) to which the image belongs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once the model was trained, I just download it and use on the web app. You can find the
 colab notebook of the model &lt;a href=&quot;https://colab.research.google.com/drive/1F0MHvQg_WqShmLh7J-fIgEvJQM-AjRb-?usp=sharing&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-web-app&quot;&gt;The web app&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Streamlit is one of the latest frameworks for creating apps in python. Its philosophy is 
to develop apps the same way you write plain Python scripts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The web app will read the uploaded image, then the classifier trained before will give its
prediction. At this point the user can say what the correct answer is and update the confusion matrix of the model.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The complete app can be found at &lt;a href=&quot;http://dinoclassifier.ml&quot;&gt;dinoclassifier.ml&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Luca Grandinetti</name></author><summary type="html">I was born in the year Jurassic Park was released and when I was 4 years old the US remake of Godzilla was distibuted. This means that as a child, like many of my generation, I was obsessed with large reptiles! Back in the day I was a bit confused about the different types of dinosaurs (T-rex, brontosaurus, stregosaurus, triceratops), which is why today I have developed an image dinosaur classifier that can also recognize the king of monsters from prehistoric reptiles.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/images/dino.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/images/dino.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">How to beat Beth Harmon</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/01/03/how-to-beat-beth-harmon.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How to beat Beth Harmon" /><published>2020-01-03T01:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2020-01-03T01:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/01/03/how-to-beat-beth-harmon</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/01/03/how-to-beat-beth-harmon.html">&lt;p&gt;After the success of &lt;em&gt;The queen’s gambit&lt;/em&gt; the game of chess has been rediscovered by a lot of players. The web-site &lt;em&gt;chess.com&lt;/em&gt; offers the possibility to play with bots that play like Beth Harmon at different ages. To face this challenge I developed a small chess engine able to play with &lt;em&gt;chess.com&lt;/em&gt; bots.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-chess-engine&quot;&gt;The chess engine&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the last years, a lot of presentations about Artificial Intelligence starts with
a slide with a Venn diagram like the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://glep93.github.io/glep93//images/ai-ml-dl.png&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t usually like this Venn diagram, it suggests the existence of AI models that
are not ML models and it opens up huge futile discussions about what it is and what it isn’t ML…
Approaching this project I found that the &lt;em&gt;classic&lt;/em&gt; chess engines are a beautiful
example of Artificial Intelligence models that are not ML, and almost every one agree about it
reducing futile discussiona. Indeed, classic chess engines
are not trained on data and so they are &lt;strong&gt;not machine learning models&lt;/strong&gt;.
However, after the appearance of &lt;em&gt;Leela Chess Zero&lt;/em&gt; in 2018 it appears a new generation of
chess engines based on deep learning techniques that learn to play chess looking at a huge
quantity of games.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For this project, I focused on classic chess engines similar to Deep Blue, the
chess computer that beat the world champion, Garry Kasparov, in 1996.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;game-tree&quot;&gt;Game tree&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A game tree is the representation of all possible matches in a game such as tic-tac-toe,
connect four, chess, or go. Any node in the tree represents a possible configuration of the board
(and history to arrive at this configuration), the edges represent the
legal moves leading from one configuration to the next.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://glep93.github.io/glep93/images/chess_Game_tree.svg&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; /&gt;
 &lt;figcaption&gt;First 2 move in chess game.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
 &lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In principle, if you can write the entire game tree of a game you have just resolved the chess game,
you can look at the tree to find the best move in any situation. The only problem
is that the game tree for chess is huge, it is estimated that it is more than 10&lt;sup&gt;120&lt;/sup&gt; (https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shannon_number) considering that the estimation of atoms in the universe is  10&lt;sup&gt;80&lt;/sup&gt;! So clearly it is not possible to write down the entire chess game tree. A solution is to compute the game tree only for a certain number of possible moves from the current position (in 1997 deep blue search to a depth of between 12 and 16 moves).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The leaves of a game-tree are end-game configurations with the win of one of the two players or a draw.
If you compute the game tree only at a certain depth you need an &lt;strong&gt;evaluation function&lt;/strong&gt;
to estimate how good is a leaf of the pruned tree.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;evaluation-function&quot;&gt;Evaluation function&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The evaluation function \( f \) is function from chess board configuration set \( B \) to real numbers \( R \).
Usually it is write in a way that \( f(x) &amp;gt; f(y) \) if \( x \) is a better
connfiguration then \( y \)  for white, morehover  \( f(x) \rightarrow \infty \)
if \(x \) is a winning configuration for white and \(f(x) \rightarrow -\infty  \) if it is a winning
configuration for black.
The moste simple evaluation function can be read as:&lt;/p&gt;

\[f(board) = \begin{cases} \infty, &amp;amp; \mbox{if } \mbox{ white wins}
 						 \\ -\infty , &amp;amp; \mbox{if } \mbox{ balck wins}
 						 \\ 0, &amp;amp; \mbox{if } n\mbox{ draw}
 						 \\ N_{white}- N_{black},  n\mbox{ else}
 						  \end{cases}\]

&lt;p&gt;Where  \(N_{white/black}  \) are the number of pieces for each player. I actualy use a slightly most
difficult evaluate function inspired from &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.chessprogramming.org/Simplified_Evaluation_Function&quot;&gt;here.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;search-algorithm&quot;&gt;Search algorithm&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now that we have an effective representation of the game and an evaluation function,
  all that’s left is to apply an algorithm that finds the right move to make.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have applied several algorithms for this purpose minmax, alphabet pruning,
  MTD-inf and MTD-bi, but for the purpose of this article I will just tell you
  about minmax.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The minmax algorithm is a greedy algorithm that approaches the problem without
 any finesse. The only idea on which it is based is that the white player will
 make his moves in order to maximize the evaluation function, while the black player
 to minimize.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first step is to “unfold” the wire tree to the maximum depth we want to reach
 (in example 4), evaluate the leaves with our evaluation function and then reconstruct
 the best path from the bottom, remembering that the black player (represented by the
 diamonds in the graph below) minimizes, while the white player (represented by the
 ellipse-shaped nodes) maximizes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
 &lt;img src=&quot;/images/minmax_movie.gif&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;min max algorithm example&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  &lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;lets-see-it-in-action-agains-beth-harmon&quot;&gt;Let’s see it in action agains Beth Harmon&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, with the help of selenium I made my chess engine interface with the site so that
automatically the two bots can clash.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=0v4bmEGi--U&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://img.youtube.com/vi/0v4bmEGi--U/0.jpg&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; /&gt;
 &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you would try to beat yourserlf Beth Harmon with python please check
&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/glep93/python_chess_engine&quot;&gt;my repository.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Luca Grandinetti</name></author><summary type="html">After the success of The queen’s gambit the game of chess has been rediscovered by a lot of players. The web-site chess.com offers the possibility to play with bots that play like Beth Harmon at different ages. To face this challenge I developed a small chess engine able to play with chess.com bots.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/images/chess.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/images/chess.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>